<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>

 <header>
  <title>Avalon Project - Features</title>
  <authors>
    <person name="Robert McIntosh" email="rmcintosh@bull-enterprises.com"/>
    <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

<body>

<s1 title="Introduction">
  <p>The Avalon project is so large and broad in scope that it is not easy
  to provide a simple list of features in the form of "Avalon provides
  Component X which will fulfill role Y in your project Z perfectly".</p>

  <p>Most of Avalon is oriented towards server development (though many parts
  can be, and are, used in other software domains). As such, it delivers all
  those features server applications require (stability, performance, etc),
  and does so very well.</p>

  <s2 title="Avalon Framework">
    <p>At the very core of our project is the Avalon Framework subproject.
    This framework is very stable and in daily use in many applications, from
    straightforward desktop products to large scale enterprise applications.<br />
    After an initial learning curve, this framework will help you
    create a better software architecture. In this way, it's role is as
    fundamental as, say Object-Oriented Programming or Design Patterns.</p>

    <p>All other avalon subprojects make use of the framework. This has allowed
    us to provide truly pluggable components which can be used in any
    programming environment without requiring gargantuan supporting applications.</p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Avalon Excalibur">
    <p>Avalon Excalibur provides you reusable components. Because our framework
    has been thought out so well, it becomes very easy to create quality
    components quickly. While many of the components in Excalibur are
    oriented towards server development (like a generic pooling implementation),
    others are very useful in other contexts as well (like utilities to help
    with internationalization).<br />
    Instead of listing the features of every single package here, I suggest you
    look at the
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/excalibur">
      Excalibur project page
    </link> for more information.</p> 
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Avalon LogKit">
    <p>Avalon LogKit is a feature-rich logging package. It can be used as an
    Alternative to other logging packages like Jakarta's
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/log4j">Log4J</link> or the (massively
    inferior)
    <link href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/docs/guide/util/logging/index.html">Logging API</link>
    included in JDK 1.4.<br />
    Please see the 
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/logkit/features.html">
      Logkit Features document
    </link> for more information.</p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Avalon Phoenix">
    <p>Phoenix is a micro-kernel. It takes care of low level application details
    so you can focus on your unique requirments. While this may sound to you
    like a servlet or EJB container, phoenix has a very different scope. Where
    you can use EJBs to connect to a database, phoenix is the basis on which to
    run that database.<br />
    With that said, you may now start to see the phoenix edge: it provides all
    of the features that make you love Servlet Engines so much (and several
    more), without restricting you to the specific servlet use case. You can
    use Avalon Phoenix to run your servlet engine, database, and other server
    components, as well as your java-enabled desktop.</p>

    <p>Take a look at the
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/phoenix">
      Phoenix project page
    </link> to learn how it manages to do all of this.</p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Avalon Applications">
    <p>Avalon Applications is a repository for Phoenix-enabled Applications.
    It contains a JDBC-compliant database, a Macromedia Flash-compatible XML socket
    server, and more. You'll also find a list of applications elsewhere on the
    web that run on phoenix. Go to the
    <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/apps">
      Applications project page
    </link> to find out all about them.</p>
  </s2>
</s1>

</body>
</document>
