<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>Avalon - Getting Started</title>
			<authors>
				<person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
			</authors>
	</header>
	<body>
		<s1 title="Introduction">
			<p>We've worked hard to write complete documentation for all the
			different parts of avalon. Unfortunately, this means there is quite
			a bit of documentation to sort through =)</p>
		</s1>

		<s1 title="Avalon for Beginners">
			<p>An effort is underway to write a concise, example-oriented guide
			to avalon that will get you up and running in about 2 minutes. You
			can find the draft
			<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/excalibur/tweety/avalon-for-beginners.html">here</link>.</p>
		</s1>

		<s1 title="Developing with Avalon">
			<p>Another really neat document is our
			<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/developing/">Developing with Avalon whitepaper</link>.
			It's quite extensive, but very thorough and well-written. If you're an
			experienced software engineer, you'll definately appreciate it.</p>
		</s1>

		<s1 title="Other documentation">
			<p>All the various subproject contain quite a bit of documentation
			as well. I'll point you in the direction of the getting started
			documentation for each of them.</p>

			<s2 title="Avalon Framework">
				<p>Both the Avalon for Beginners and the Developing with Avalon
				paper introduce you to avalon framework. We suggest you start
				with one of these.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Avalon Excalibur">
				<p>Unfortunately, the Excalibur documentation as a whole is in
				bad shape, though some of the components it contains have really
				complete documentation otherwise.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Avalon Cornerstone">
				<p>Much the same is true for the cornerstone documentation. We
				suggest you read the
				<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/cornerstone">overview</link>, then
				browse the
				<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/cornerstone/api">javadocs</link>
				for more information.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Avalon Phoenix">
				<p>The
				<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/phoenix/getting-started.html">Avalon Phoenix getting started document</link>
				desribes the HelloWorld demo Service demo. Tt will take you
				through downloading, installing and then running the demo step
				by step so it is an easy place tp start</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Avalon Logkit">
				<p>You will most likely not use logkit by itself, but
				rather with Phoenix or another container, so you don't normally
				need to learn much about logkit. If you are interested in learning
				more about it, there's a really good
				<link href="@AVALON_BASE@/logkit/whitepaper.html">whitepaper</link>
				on it (it doesn't have a real 'getting started' document).</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Avalon Applications">
				<p>The Phoenix documentation takes you through setting up the
				Demo application; for the others there is no getting started
				documentation.</p>
			</s2>
		</s1>

		<s1 title="When you do get lost...">
			<p>When you get stuck in sources, documentation, and the mailing list archive,
			post your questions to the user mailing list (information on it is
			<link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">here</link>). For
			many, Avalon poses a steep learning curve, and we'll try and help you
			flatten it as much as we can.</p>
		</s1>
	</body>
	<footer>
		<legal>
		Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
		$Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006-08-08 23:17:21 $
		</legal>
	</footer>
</document>
