<?xml version="1.0"?>

<announcement>
  <title>@Name@ @version@</title>
  <abstract>The Avalon team is proud to announce the @version@ @status@ release
of the @Name@.</abstract>

  <project site="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon">
    <title>Avalon</title>
    <description>
      The Avalon project is Apache's Java Server Framework. It is
      separated into five sub projects: Framework, Excalibur, LogKit,
      Cornerstone, and Phoenix. Its purpose is to simplify
      server side programming for Java based projects.  It
      formalizes serveral best of breed practices and patterns for
      server side programming.
    </description>
  </project>

  <project site="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/@name@">
    <title>@Name@ @version@</title>
    <description>
      <para>
        The Avalon Framework formalizes the contracts and patterns used in the 
        other Avalon projects. It is derived from modern software engineering
        techniques and aims to provide a solid basis on which to build server
        products.
      </para>
      <para>
        What that means is that we define the central interface Component.  We
	also define the relationship (contract) a component has with peers,
	ancestors and children. This documentation introduces you to those
	patterns, interfaces, and relationships.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Avalon Framework raises the abstraction level from Object-Oriented
	Programming concept one notch to the Component-Oriented Programming
	model.  This enables programmers to concern themselves with assemblies
	of classes, rather than the classes themselves--thus reducing the
	number of things the programmer must keep in mind, and speeding up
	application development.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Avalon Framework is already used in
	<ulink uri="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon">Cocoon</ulink>, an XML
	publishing framework.  The Avalon Framework is also used in
	<ulink uri="http://jakarta.apache.org/james">Apache JAMES</ulink>, a
	Java(tm) Mail Server.  Another project that is built on Avalon Framework
	is <ulink uri="http://www.jesktop.org">Jestkop</ulink>, a cross-platform
	replacement for your ordinary desktop.  If you are evaluating Avalon
	and want the proof that it's claims are valid check them out.
      </para>
    </description>
    <changes version="@version@" file="changes.xml"/>
    <downloads name="Avalon" base="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-avalon/release/@name@"/>
  </project>

</announcement>

