<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon Framework - Guide - What is COP?</title>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <authors>
      <person name="Leo Simons" email="leosimons@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction"> 
      <p>
        Component Oriented Programming, or COP for short, takes Object Oriented
        Programming one step further. Regular OOP organizes data object into
        entities that take care of themselves. There are many advantages to this
        approach. I'll assume that you, being a java programmer, are familiar
        with those.
      </p>
      <p>
        It also has a big limitation: that of object co-dependency. To remove that
        limitation, a more rigid idea had to be formalized: the Component. The key
        difference between a regular object and a component is that a component is
        completely replaceable.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="COP is not just a buzzword">
      <p>
        There is a lot of buzz in the industry touting Component Based Design
	(CBD).  You will find, that the definition of a Component in Avalon
	is more formal than most companies' definition of a Component.  Any
	system developed with the principles of Avalon can claim CBD.  In
	fact the Avalon Framework formalizes CBD more rigidly than the marketing
	definition.  Do not be fooled though, CBD and COP aren't necessarily
	the same thing.  Component Based Design refers to how a system is
	designed and not how it is implemented.  Component Oriented Programming,
	on the other hand, refers to how a system is implemented and not how
	it is designed.  In practice, you can't implement COP without first
	designing with Components in mind.
      </p>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006-08-08 23:17:20 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>

