<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN"
                         "./dtd/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:base="context://content/xdocs/developing/">
  <chapterinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <xi:xinclude href="../authors/bloritsch.xml"/>
    </authorgroup>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Framework and Foundations</title>
  <subtitle>
    We will describe Avalon's contracts and interfaces so we have a foundation
    to actually build our Components.
  </subtitle>
  <para>
    Avalon Framework is the central piece to the entire Avalon project.  If you
    understand the contracts and constructs defined in the framework, you can
    understand anything that uses it.  Remember the principles and patterns we
    have already discussed so far.  In this section, we will expound on how the
    Role concept works practically, the lifecycle of Components, and how the
    interfaces work.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Defining the Component's Role</title>
    <para>
      In Avalon, all Components have a role.  The reason is that you retrieve
      your Components by role.  At this stage, the only concern area we are
      using is the signature of the role.  If you recall in the second section,
      we defined a Component as "the combination of a work interface and the
      implementation of the interface".  That work interface is your role.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Creating the Role's Interface</title>
      <para>
        Below you will find an example interface, followed by some best
        practices along with their reasoning.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
package org.apache.bizserver.docs;

public interface DocumentRepository extends Component
{
    String ROLE = DocumentRepository.class.getName();

    Document getDocument(Principal requestor, int refId);
}
]]>
      </programlisting>
      <section>
        <title>Best Practices</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Include a String called "ROLE" that has the role's official name.
              That name is the same as the fully qualified name for the work
              interface.  This helps later on when we need to get an instance
              of the Component later.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Do extend the Component interface if possible.  This makes it easier
              on you when it is time to release your Component.  If you are not
              in control of the work interface, then you do not have this option.
              It is not the end of the world, as you can recast the instance to
              <classname>Component</classname> when it is time to release it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Do one thing and do it well.  A Component should have the simplest
              interface possible, When your work interface extends several other
              interfaces, you muddy the contract for this Component.  An old
              American acronym helps define this pattern: Keep It Simple, Stupid
              (KISS).  It's not hard to outsmart yourself&mdash;I've done it
              a number of times myself.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Only specify the methods you need.  The client should have no
              knowledge of implementation details, and too many alternative
              methods only introduce unneeded complexity.  In other words pick
              an approach and stick with it.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Don't let your Role's interface extend any lifecycle or lifestyle
              interfaces.  By implementing any of those classes of interfaces, you
              are tying an implementation to the specification.  This is a
              bad pattern and this will only lead to debugging and implementation
              problems later.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Choosing the Role's Name</title>
        <para>
          In Avalon, every Role has a name. It is how you get references to
          other Components in the system.  The Avalon team has outlined some
          idioms to follow for the naming of your role.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Naming Idioms</title>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The fully qualified name of the work interface is usually the
                role name.  The exceptions are listed after this general rule.
                Using this example, our theoretical Component's name would be
                "org.apache.bizserver.docs.DocumentRepository".  This is the
                name that would be included in your interface's "ROLE"
                property.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If we obtain the reference to this Component through a
                Component Selector, we usually take the role name derived from
                the first rule and append the word "Selector" to the end.  The
                result of this naming rule would be
                "org.apache.bizserver.docs.DocumentRepositorySelector".  You
                can use the shorthand
                <parameter>DocumentRepository.ROLE + "Selector"</parameter>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If we have multiple Components that implement the same work
                interface, but are used for different purposes, we have
                separate roles.  A Role is the Component's purpose in the
                system.  Each role name will start with the original role
                name, but the purpose name of the role will be appended
                with a <parameter>/${purpose}</parameter>.  By example
                we could have the following purposes for our
                DocumentRepository: PurchaseOrder and Bill.  Our two roles
                would be expressed as
                <parameter>DocumentRepository.ROLE + "/PurchaseOrder"</parameter>
                and <parameter>DocuementRepository.ROLE + "/Bill"</parameter>,
                respectively.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Overview of Framework Interfaces</title>
    <para>
      The entire Avalon Framework can be divided into seven main categories (as
      is the API): Activity, Component, Configuration, Context, Logger,
      Parameters, Thread, and Miscellany.  Each of those categories (except
      Miscellany) represents a unique concern area.  It is common for a
      Component to implement several interfaces to identify all the concern
      areas that the Component is worried about.  This will allow the
      Component's container to manage each Component in a consistent manner.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Lifecycle for Avalon Interfaces</title>
      <para>
        When a framework implements several interfaces to separate the concerns
        of the Component, there is potential for confusion over the order of
        method calls.  Avalon Framework realizes this, and so we developed the
        contract for lifecycle ordering of events.  If your Component does not
        implement the associated Interface, then simply skip to the next event
        that will be called.  Because there is a correct way to create and
        prepare Components, you can set up your Components as you receive
        events.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Lifecycle of a Component is split into three phases:
        Initialization, Active Service, and Destruction.  Because these phases
        are sequential, we will discuss the events in order.  In addition, the
        act of Construction and Finalization is implicit due to the Java
        language, so they will be skipped.  The steps will list the method
        name, and the required interface.  Within each phase, there will be a
        number of stages identified by method names.  Those stages are executed
        if your Component extends the associated interface specified in
        parenthesis.
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Initialization</title>
        <para>
          This list of stages occurs in this specific order, and occurs only
          once during the life of the Component.
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>enableLogging</function>
              [<classname>LogEnabled</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>contextualize</function>
              [<classname>Contextualizable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>compose</function>
              [<classname>Composable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>configure</function>
             [<classname>Configurable</classname>]
              <emphasis>or</emphasis>
              <function>parameterize</function>
             [<classname>Parameterizable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>initialize</function>
              [<classname>Initializable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>start</function>
              [<classname>Startable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Active Service</title>
        <para>
          This list of stages occurs in this specific order, but may occur
          multiple times during the life of the Component.  Please note that
          should you choose to not implement the Suspendable interface, it is
          up to your Component to ensure proper functionality while executing
          any of the Re* stages.
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>suspend</function>
              [<classname>Suspendable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>recontextualize</function>
              [<classname>Recontextualizable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>recompose</function>
              [<classname>Recomposable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>reconfigure</function>
              [<classname>Reconfigurable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>resume</function>
              [<classname>Suspendable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Destruction</title>
        <para>
          This list of stages occurs in the order specified, and occurs only
          once during the life of the Component.
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>stop</function>
              [<classname>Startable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <function>dispose</function>
              [<classname>Disposable</classname>]
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Avalon Framework Contracts</title>
      <para>
        In this section, we will cover all the sections alphabetically with
        the exception of the most important concern area: Component.
      </para>
      <note>
        <title>A Word About Containers</title>
        <para>
          When I use the word "container" or "contains" when describing
          Components, I have a very specific meaning.  I am referring to child
          Components that the parent Component has instantiated and controls.
          I am not referring to Components obtained through a ComponentManager
          or ComponentSelector.  Furthermore, some Avalon stages received by a
          container must be propagated to all of its children implementing the
          appropriate interface.  The specific interfaces in question are
          Initializable, Startable, Suspendable, and Disposable.  The reasoning
          for this contract is that these particular interfaces have specific
          execution contracts.
        </para>
      </note>
      <section>
        <title>Component</title>
        <para>
          This is the core of Avalon Framework.  Any interface defined in this
          concern area will throw ComponentException.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Component</title>
          <para>
            Every Avalon Component <emphasis>must</emphasis> implement the
            Component interface.  The Component Manager and Component Selector
            only handle Components.  There are no methods associated with this
            interface.  It is only used as a marker interface.
          </para>
          <para>
            Any Component must use default no parameter constructors.  All
            configurations are done with the
            <classname>Configurable</classname> or
            <classname>Parameterizable</classname> interfaces.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Composable</title>
          <para>
            A Component that uses other Components needs to implement this
            interface.  The interface has only one method
            <function>compose</function> with a
            <classname>ComponentManager</classname> passed in as the only
            parameter.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>compose</function> is called once and only once during
            the lifetime of this Component.
          </para>
          <para>
            This interface along with any other interface that has methods
            specified uses the Inversion of Control pattern.  It is called by
            the Component's container, and only the Components that this
            Component needs should be present in the
            <classname>ComponentManager</classname>.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Recomposable</title>
          <para>
            On rare occasions, a Component will need a new
            <classname>ComponentManager</classname> with new Component role
            mappings.  For those occasions, implement the recomposable
            interface.  It has a separate method from Composable called
            <function>recompose</function>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding the interface states that the
            <function>recompose</function> method can be called any number of
            times, but never before the Component is fully initialized.  When
            this method is called, the Component must update itself in a safe
            and consistent manner.  Usually this means all processing that the
            Component is performing must stop before the update and resume
            after the update.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Activity</title>
        <para>
          This group of interfaces refers to contracts for the life cycle of
          the Component.  If there is an error during any method call with this
          group of interfaces, then you can throw a generic Exception.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Disposable</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Disposable</classname> interface is used by any
            Component that wants a structured way of knowing it is no longer
            needed.  Once a Component is disposed of, it can no longer be used.
            In fact, it should be awaiting garbage collection.  The interface
            only has one method <function>dispose</function> that has no
            parameters.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>dispose</function> method is called once and the method
            is the last one called during the life of the Component.  Further
            implications include that the Component will no longer be used,
            and all resources held by this Component must be released.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Initializable</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Initializable</classname> interface is used by any
            Component that needs to create Components or perform
            initializations that take information from other initialization
            steps.  The interface only has one method
            <function>initialize</function> that has no parameters.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>initialize</function> method is called once and the
            method is the last one called during the initialization sequence.
            Further implications include that the Component is now live, and it
            can be used by other Components in the system.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Startable</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Startable</classname> interface is used by any
            Component that is constantly running for the duration of its life.
            The interface defines two methods: <function>start</function> and
            <function>stop</function>.  Neither method has any parameters.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>start</function> method is called once after the
            Component is fully initialized, and the <function>stop</function>
            method is called once before the Component is disposed of.  Neither
            method will be called more than once, and <function>start</function>
            will always be called before <function>stop</function>.
            Implications of using this interface require that the
            <function>start</function> and <function>stop</function> methods be
            conducted safely (unlike the <function>Thread.stop</function>
            method) and not render the system unstable.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Suspendable</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Suspendable</classname> interface is used by any
            Component that is running for the duration of its life that permits
            itself to be suspended.  While it is most commonly used in
            conjunction with the <classname>Startable</classname> interface, it
            is not required to do so.  The interface defines two methods:
            <function>suspend</function> and <function>resume</function>.
            Neither method has any parameters.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that
            <function>suspend</function> and <function>resume</function> may be
            called any number of times, but never before the Component is
            initialized and started or after the Component is stopped and
            disposed.  Calls to <function>suspend</function> when the system is
            already suspended should have no effect as well as calls to
            <function>resume</function> when the system is already running.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Configuration</title>
        <para>
          This group of interfaces describes the concern area of configuration.
          If there are any problems, such as required
          <classname>Configuration</classname> elements that are missing, then
          you may throw a <classname>ConfigurationException</classname>.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Configurable</title>
          <para>
            Components that modify their exact behavior based on configurations
            must implement this interface to obtain an instance of the
            <classname>Configuration</classname> object.  There is one method
            associated with this interface: <function>configure</function> with
            a <classname>Configuration</classname> object as the only
            parameter.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>configure</function> method is called once during the
            life of the Component.  The <classname>Configuration</classname>
            object passed in <emphasis>must not be null</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Configuration</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Configuration</classname> object is a representation
            of a tree of configuration elements that have attributes.  In a
            way, you can view the configuration object as an overly simplified
            DOM.  There are too many methods to cover in this document, so
            please review the JavaDocs.  You can get the
            <classname>Configuration</classname> object's value as a
            <parameter>String</parameter>, <parameter>int</parameter>,
            <parameter>long</parameter>, <parameter>float</parameter>, or
            <parameter>boolean</parameter>&mdash;all with default values.  You
            can do the same for attribute values.  You may also get child
            <classname>Configuration</classname> objects.
          </para>
          <para>
            There is a contract that says that if a
            <classname>Configuration</classname> object has a value that it
            should not have any children, and the corollary is also
            true&mdash;if there are any children, there should be no value.
          </para>
          <para>
            You will notice that you may not get parent
            <classname>Configuration</classname> objects.  This is by design.
            To reduce the complexity of the <classname>Configuration</classname>
            system, containers will most likely pass child configuration
            objects to child Components.  The child Components should not have
            any access to parent configuration values.  This approach might
            provide a little inconvenience, but the Avalon team opted for
            security by design in every instance where there was a tradeoff.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Reconfigurable</title>
          <para>
            Components that implement this interface behave very similar to
            <classname>Recomposable</classname> Components.  It's only method
            is named <function>reconfigure</function>.  This design decision is
            used to minimize the learning curve of the Re* interfaces.
            <classname>Reconfigurable</classname> is to
            <classname>Configurable</classname> as
            <classname>Recomposable</classname> is to
            <classname>Composable</classname>.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Context</title>
        <para>
          The concept of the <classname>Context</classname> in Avalon arose
          from the need to provide a mechanism to pass simple objects from a
          container to a Component.  The exact protocol and binding names are
          purposely left undefined to provide the greatest flexibility to
          developers.  The contracts surrounding the use of the
          <classname>Context</classname> object are left for you to define in
          your system, however the mechanism is the same.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Context</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Context</classname> interface defines only the
            method <function>get</function>.  It has an
            <parameter>Object</parameter> for a parameter, and it returns an
            object based on that key.  The <classname>Context</classname> is
            populated by the container, and passed to the child Component who
            only has access to <emphasis>read</emphasis> the
            <classname>Context</classname>.
          </para>
          <para>
            There is no set contract with the <classname>Context</classname>
            other than it should always be <emphasis>read-only</emphasis> by
            the child Component.  If you extend Avalon's
            <classname>Context</classname>, please respect that contract.  It
            is part of the Inversion of Control pattern as well as security by
            design.  In addition, it is a bad idea to pass a reference to the
            container in the Context for the same reason that the Context
            should be <emphasis>read-only</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Contextualizable</title>
          <para>
            A Component that wishes to receive the container's
            <classname>Context</classname> will implement this interface.  It
            has one method named <function>contextualize</function> with the
            parameter being the container's <classname>Context</classname>
            object.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this interface is that the
            <function>contextualize</function> method is called once during the
            life of a Component, after <classname>LogEnabled</classname> but
            before any other initialization method.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Recontextualizable</title>
          <para>
            Components that implement this interface behave very similar to
            <classname>Recomposable</classname> Components.  It's only method
            is named <function>recontextualize</function>.  This design
            decision is used to minimize the learning curve of the Re*
            interfaces.  <classname>Recontextualizable</classname> is to
            <classname>Contextualizable</classname> as
            <classname>Recomposable</classname> is to
            <classname>Composable</classname>.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Resolvable</title>
          <para>
            The Resolvable interface is used to mark objects that need to be
            resolved in some particular context.  An example might be an object
            that is shared by multiple <classname>Context</classname> objects,
            and modifies its behavior based on a particular
            <classname>Context</classname>.  The <function>resolve</function>
            method is called by the <classname>Context</classname> before the
            object is returned.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Logger</title>
        <para>
          Every system needs the ability to log events.  Avalon uses its
          LogKit project internally.  While LogKit does have ways of accessing
          a Logger instance statically, the Framework wishes to use the
          Inversion of Control pattern.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>LogEnabled</title>
          <para>
            Every Component that needs a Logger instance implements this
            interface.  The interface has one method named
            <function>enableLogging</function> and passes Avalon Framework's
            <classname>Logger</classname> instance to the Component.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract surrounding this method is that it is called only
            once during the Component's lifecycle before any other
            initialization step.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Logger</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Logger</classname> interface is used to abstract
            away the differences in logging libraries.  It provides only a
            client API.  Avalon Framework provides three wrapper classes that
            implement this interface: <classname>LogKitLogger</classname> for
            LogKit, <classname>Log4jLogger</classname> for Log4J, and
            <classname>Jdk14Logger</classname> for JDK 1.4 logging.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Parameters</title>
        <para>
          Avalon realizes that the Configuration object hierarchy can be
          heavy in many circumstances.  Therefore, we came up with a
          <classname>Parameters</classname> object that captures the
          convenience of <classname>Configuration</classname> objects with a
          simple name and value pair.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Parameterizable</title>
          <para>
            Any Component that wants to use <classname>Parameters</classname>
            instead of <classname>Configuration</classname> objects will
            implement this interface.  <classname>Parameterizable</classname>
            has one method named <function>parameterize</function> with the
            parameter being the <classname>Parameters</classname> object.
          </para>
          <para>
            The contract is that this is called once during the lifecycle of
            the Component.  This interface is not compatible with the
            <classname>Configurable</classname> interface.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Parameters</title>
          <para>
            The <classname>Parameters</classname> object provides a mechanism
            to obtain a value based on a <parameter>String</parameter> name.
            There are convenience methods that allow you to use defaults if the
            value does not exist, as well as obtain the value in any of the
            same formats that are in the <classname>Configurable</classname>
            interface.
          </para>
          <para>
            While there are similarities between the
            <classname>Parameters</classname> object and the
            <classname>java.util.Property</classname> object, there are some
            important semantic differences.  First,
            <classname>Parameters</classname> are
            <emphasis>read-only</emphasis>. Second,
            <classname>Parameters</classname> are easily derived from
            <classname>Configuration</classname> objects.  Lastly, the
            <classname>Parameters</classname> object is derived from XML
            fragments that look like this:
          </para>
          <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<parameter name="param-name" value="param-value"/>
]]>
          </programlisting>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Thread</title>
        <para>
          The thread marker interfaces are used to signal to the container
          essential semantic information regarding the Component use.  They
          mark a component implementation in regards to thread safety.  It is
          a best practice to delay implementing these interfaces until the
          final Component implementation class.  This avoids complications
          when an implementation is marked <classname>ThreadSafe</classname>,
          but a component that extends that implementation is not.  The
          interfaces defined in this package comprise part of what I call
          the <emphasis>LifeStyle</emphasis> interfaces.  There is one more
          <emphasis>LifeStyle</emphasis> interface that is part of the
          Excalibur package&mdash;so it is an extension to this core
          set&mdash;<classname>Poolable</classname> that is defined in
          Excalibur's pool implementations.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>SingleThreaded</title>
          <para>
            The contract with <classname>SingleThreaded</classname> Components
            is that the interface or the implementation precludes this
            Component being accessed by several threads simultaneously.  Each
            thread needs its own instance of the Component.  Alternatively, you
            may use Component pooling instead of creating a new instance for
            every request for the Component.  In order to use pooling, you will
            need to implement Avalon Excalibur's <classname>Poolable</classname>
            interface instead of this one.
          </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>ThreadSafe</title>
          <para>
            The contract with <classname>ThreadSafe</classname> Components is
            that both their interface and their implementation function
            correctly no matter how many threads access the Component
            simultaneously.  While this is generally a lofty design goal,
            sometimes it is simply not possible due to the technologies you are
            using.  A Component that implements this interface will generally
            only have one instance available in the system, and other
            Components will use that one instance.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Miscellany</title>
        <para>
          The classes and interfaces in the root package for Avalon Framework
          incorporates Cascading Exceptions, and a couple of generic utilities.
          However, one class deserves mention beyond the others.
        </para>
        <section>
          <title>Version</title>
          <para>
            <trademark>Java</trademark> versioning techniques are entries in
            the manifest file in a jar.  The problem is, when the jar is
            unpacked you lose the versioning information, and the versioning
            is in an easily modified text file.  When you couple this with a
            higher learning curve, detecting Component or Interface versions
            is difficult.
          </para>
          <para>
            The Avalon team came up with the Version object to allow you to
            have easily determined versions, and to compare versions.  You may
            implement the <classname>Version</classname> object in your
            Components and your tests for the proper Component or minimum
            version level will be much easier.
          </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
