<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN"
                         "./dtd/docbookx.dtd">

<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:base="context://content/xdocs/developing/">
  <title>Developing With Apache Avalon</title>
  <subtitle>Apache Avalon Project</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Developing With Apache Avalon</title>
    <subtitle>Apache Avalon Project</subtitle>
    <authorgroup>
      <xi:include href="../authors/bloritsch.xml"/>
    </authorgroup>
    <edition>Developer's Guide version 1.0 for Avalon Framework</edition>
    <pubdate>2001</pubdate>
    <copyright>
      <year>2001</year>
      <holder>Apache Software Foundation</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
        without modification, are permitted provided that the following
        conditions are met:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Redistributions of  source code must  retain the above
            copyright  notice, this list of conditions and the following
            disclaimer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
            copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
            disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials
            provided with the distribution.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The end-user documentation included with the redistribution,
            if any, must include the following  acknowledgment:
            "This product includes software developed by the Apache
            Software Foundation  (http://www.apache.org/)."  Alternately,
            this  acknowledgment may  appear in the software itself,  if
            and wherever such third-party acknowledgments normally appear.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The names "Jakarta", "Apache Avalon", "Avalon Excalibur",
            "Avalon Framework" and "Apache Software Foundation" must not
            be used to endorse or promote products derived from this
            software without prior written permission. For written
            permission, please contact apache@apache.org.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Products  derived from this software may not be called
            "Apache", nor may "Apache" appear in their name, without
            prior written permission of the Apache Software Foundation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED
        WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES
        OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
        DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE APACHE SOFTWARE  FOUNDATION
        OR ITS CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR  ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
        SPECIAL,  EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL  DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT
        LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT  OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS
        OF USE, DATA, OR  PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
        CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT
        LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING  NEGLIGENCE OR  OTHERWISE) ARISING IN
        ANY WAY OUT OF THE  USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
        POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
      </para>
      <para>
        This software  consists of voluntary contributions made by many
        individuals on behalf of the Apache Software Foundation. For more
        information on the Apache Software Foundation, please see
        &lt;http://www.apache.org/&gt;.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        <trademark class="trade">Java</trademark> and all Java-based
        trademarks and logos are trademarks or registered trademarks
        of Sun Microsystems, Inc., in the United States and other
        countries.  The Apache Software Foundation is independant of
        Sun Microsystems.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <xi:include href="changes.xml"/>
  </bookinfo>
  <dedication>
    <para>
      This developer's guide is dedicated to the three people who's vision
      started the Avalon project: Federico Barbieri, Stefano Mazzocchi, and
      Pierpaolo Fumagalli.  Their concept for the Avalon project has stood
      the test of time.
    </para>
  </dedication>
  <toc/>
  <xi:include href="introduction.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="decomposing.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="framework.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="implementing.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="conclusion.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="changes.xml"/>
</book>


