<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>History</title>
    <subtitle>How to write servers using Avalon</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person id="PF" name="Pierpaolo Fumagalli" email="pier@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
    <notice>
      This documentation is provided for historical purposes to document the
      beginnings of Avalon.
    </notice>
    <abstract>
      In this document I try to explain how a server could be developed
      using the benefits offered by the Java Apache Server Framework
      (Avalon) and I introduce the reader to the concept of what a
      <code>Block</code> is.
    </abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction: Servers and Services?">
      <p>
        It's somehow difficult to give a proper definition of &quot;server&quot;,
        due to the confusion created in the time so far by the different meanings
        that term had, facing the different evolution of the technologies.
      </p>
      <p>
        The term &quot;server&quot; is commonly used with at least three different
        meanings:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <strong>&quot;Server&quot; as computer:</strong> With this meaning the
          server term is intended to be the computer sharing resources.
          <br/>
          <em>
            Ex. Our corporate &quot;server&quot; is a double Pentium II
            running at 450 MHz with 12 GB of SCSI hard disk running Linux.
          </em>
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>&quot;Server&quot; as a program:</strong> With this meaning the
          server term is intended to be the application that enables the
          resource sharing, not caring about the network protocols it
          implements.
          <br/>
          <em>
            Ex. Our Mail server is FlosieTek FTGate release 2.1 which
            implements the SMTP and POP3 protocols.
          </em>
        </li>
        <li>
          <strong>&quot;Server&quot; as a protocol handler:</strong> With this meaning
          the server term is intended to be the application that enables
          the access to shared resources via a specified protocol.
          <br/>
          <em>
            Ex. Our HTTP server is Apache 1.3.4.
          </em>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        While we can clearly see the difference between the first definition of
        &quot;server&quot; (computer) and the other two (applications), it's hard
        to see the difference between the second definition (&quot;server&quot; as
        a multi-protocol handler) and the third (&quot;server&quot; as a single
        protocol handler).
      </p>
      <p>
        Since it's crucial for all developers involved in the Avalon project to
        share the same common idea of &quot;server&quot;, I would like to define
        a server as a <strong>protocol handler</strong>. We would, then, have HTTP servers,
        SMTP servers or POP3 servers, but we cannot use the term MAIL server.
      </p>
      <p>
        What we called the mail server is in fact the union of two (or more)
        different &quot;server&quot;s (in our example the union of a SMTP and a
        POP3 server).
      </p>
      <p>
        We can clearly see, anyway, that a POP3 and an SMTP server will have to
        share most resources and code to build up a complete mailing system, like,
        for example, a central repository where messages could be stored. We would
        then define the union of the SMTP server, the POP3 server and the central
        messages repository (we could call it <strong>Mail Engine</strong>) as a Mail
        &quot;service&quot;. To clarify things a little bit, maybe a picture would
        help:
      </p>
      <figure src="images/server-01.gif" alt="Server 1"/>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Dividing the code">
      <p>
        We can clearly see, however, how this approach to the problem brings to
        a monolithic implementation of the code, not allowing, or making really
        difficult, for other persons to add features, for example, integrating an
        IMAP server within our Mail Service.
      </p>
      <p>
        In fact, if we don't clearly separate the code (and a good developer
        should always keep in mind his server expansion) adding a feature like an
        IMAP server into our service could become hell, and, most developers will
        try to find other solutions already in the market rather than using and
        improving what we have done.
      </p>
      <p>
        The solution would be to have a sort of "in-core" modularization of our
        server.... To be continued...
      </p>
      <figure src="images/server-02.gif" alt="Server 2"/>
      <figure src="images/server-03.gif" alt="Server 3"/>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The concept of a Block">
      <figure src="images/server-04.gif" alt="Server 4"/>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The Avalon Framework">
      <fixme author="PF">We need some info in here.</fixme>
    </s1>
  </body>
  <footer>
    <legal>
      Copyright (c) @year@ The Jakarta Apache Project All rights reserved.
      $Revision: 1.1 $ $Date: 2006-08-08 23:17:21 $
    </legal>
  </footer>
</document>
